Indiana University Committee on Historic Preservation records, 1968-1989 C9
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Committee on Historic Preservation records
1968-1989
1977-1988
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. Committee on Historic Preservation (1988-)
C9
2.4 cubic feet 3 boxes
Established in 1968 by then Interim President Herman B Wells, the Committee on Historic Preservation sought to provide a leadership role on historic preservation efforts across the State of Indiana. The collection consists of correspondence, memos, and reports created and collected by Donald F. Carmony, who served as the first chair until 1971 and John B. Patton, who served as chair from 1974-1978.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The University Committee on Historic Preservation was established in 1968 by then-interim president Herman B Wells "to provide a means for discussion and recommendation of ways in which the University might take a leadership role in identifying the problems of historic preservation in the state of Indiana and in indicating how those problems could be met." He further suggested that the committee might investigate ways of developing historic buildings and museums and that it might sponsor conferences, tours, and the collection of data.
Donald F. Carmony was named the first chair of the committee, a position he held until 1971. University president John Ryan appointed a University Heritage Committee in 1976, chaired by University Chancellor Herman B Wells for the period from 1976-1987. The Heritage Committee included a Subcommittee on Historic Preservation (chaired by John B. Patton, 1977-1988), which was created to deal with preservation issues as they related to university buildings and properties. The University Committee on Historic Preservation was absorbed by the Subcommittee in 1986. In 1987, however, the subcommittee's parent, the University Heritage Committee, was dissolved, and the following year the Subcommittee was re-appointed at a university-wide level as the University Committee on Historic Preservation. Donald F. Carmony was named chairman, succeeding Patton. Carmony was succeeded by Philip Scarpino in 1989.
A notable subcommittee of the University Committee on Historic Preservation has been the Cornelius O'Brien Lecture Series Committee which was organized in 1972 to administer the lecture series on preservation begun with donations by the O'Brien family. The O'Brien Lecture Committee had independent status as a university-level committee from 1977-1988, but became a part of the Historic Preservation committee again at that point. The O'Brien Committee was chaired by Donald F. Carmony, 1972-1980, 1988-1989, and by John B. Patton, 1980-1988.
Another important activity of the University Committee on Historic Preservation has been to arrange an annual conference on historic preservation, which first occurred in 1969 has been held at various locations around the state.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into three series: Administrative files, Cornelius O'Brien Lecture Series and Conference on Historic Preservation files.
Scope and Content Note
With materials dating from 1969 through 1989, the Indiana University Historic Preservation records consist of three separate series: Administrative files, the Cornelius O'Brien Lecture files and the Conference on Historic Preservation files. The Administrative files series (1968-1986) consists of annual reports, committee appointments, meetings minutes, agendas, and records pertaining to training programs in historic preservation.
The Cornelius O'Brien Lecture series (1968-1989) includes grant proposals for the Lilly Endowment and Irvin-Sweeney-Miller Foundation, committee appointments, and meeting minutes, as well as correspondence concerning speakers for the lecture series. There are print items about the New Harmony historic site and the Veraestau Indiana landmark.
Finally, the Conference on Historic Preservation series (1969-1989) includes files for the annual Historic Preservation Conferences. Records include correspondence written to and from the conference planning committee, news releases about the annual conferences, print brochures for the conferences, and proceedings for panel discussions. This series also includes evaluations and suggestions from conference attendees from the first two conferences held in 1969 and 1970.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
Accession 0539, 0540
Provenance
Collection came from the offices of John B. Patton, who served as the committee chair from 1974-1978 and Donald F. Carmony who served as the first chair until 1971.
Historic preservation --Indiana --Bloomington --History --Sources.; Indiana University. Committee on Historic Preservation (1968-1986) -- Archives; Indiana University. Committee on Historic Preservation (1988-) -- Archives; Indiana University. Committee on Historic Preservation (1988-) -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Committee on Historic Preservation (1968-1986) -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Heritage Committee. Subcommittee on Historic Preservation -- Archives; Indiana University. Heritage Committee. Subcommittee on Historic Preservation -- Records and correspondence
- Administrative files, 1968-1986
  - University Committee on Historic Preservation, 1968-1986
    - Annual Reports, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Committee Appointments, 1968-1984 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, reprints, brochures, 1974-1983 (Box 1)
    - Cochran House, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Historic Preservation Programs for Indiana Grant Proposal, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Historic Trails Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - IU Historic New Harmony Institute, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and related materials (Box 1)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 1)
      - 1972-1986 (Box 1)
    - New Harmony Commission, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - Training programs in historic preservation, 1979 (Box 1)
  - University Heritage Committee, 1976-1986
    - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1986 (Box 1)
- Cornelius O'Brien Lecture Series, 1968-1989
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1983 (Box 2)
  - Appointments, 1974-1988 (Box 2)
  - Committee Appointments, 1968-1974 (Box 2)
  - Committee Meetings, 1972-1985 (Box 2)
  - Committee Membership, 1977-1983 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
      - 1968 (Box 2)
      - 1969 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1971-1986 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1988 (Box 2)
      - 1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 2)
    - Mary O'Brien Gibson (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Robert Utley, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Establishment of Lecture Series, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Grant Proposal to Lilly Endowment, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Grant Proposal to Irwin-Sweeney-Miller Foundation, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Historic Landmarks Foundation of Indiana, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
  - Lecture Series (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Members, Agenda and Minutes, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Membership, 1968-1977 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous financial correspondence with Foundation, 1975-1985 (Box 2)
  - Resource Persons, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Speakers (Box 2)
    - A-Be, 1974-1983 (Box 2)
    - Bi-Bo, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
    - Br-Bre, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
    - Bri-C, 1979-1982 (Box 2)
    - D-F, 1978-1987 (Box 2)
    - G, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - H-He, 1976-1986 (Box 2)
    - Hi-Ho, 1978-1987 (Box 2)
    - J-K, 1985 (Box 2)
    - L, 1979-1987 (Box 3)
    - M, 1977-1985 (Box 3)
    - O, 1980 (Box 3)
    - P-Pe, 1981-1986 (Box 3)
    - Pi-R, 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    - S-T, 1976-1983 (Box 3)
    - U, 1974-1981 (Box 3)
    - W-Z, 1973-1986 (Box 3)
  - Speakers Approval and Compensation, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Speakers Pending, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - Possible Speakers, 1972-1978 (Box 3)
  - Veraestau (Box 3)
    - Lecture Series, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
    - Observance, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Family Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - Speeches, 1975 (Box 3)
- Conference on Historic Preservation, 1969-1989
  - General (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
  - Evaluations and Suggestions, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Evaluation of 1970 Preservation Conference (Box 3)
  - Conference on Historical Preservation Grants, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Conference Liaison Representatives, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Conference Liaison, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Preservation Conference, Program, details re: correspondence, thank you letters, and proceedings, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Plans for and Items re: 1970 Preservation Conference (Box 3)